[Music]
welcome back to Voice club this is a
shorter podcast and one of three to come
with my friend and brother on the way
Samuel Austin
Simon's the founder of live learn
evolved.com a digital portal for wisdom
curiosity and transformation he's a
designer yoga teacher psychonaut and
student of zen alchemy and esoteric
wisdom this is a short dialogue about
navigating mental loops and surrendering
the ego in psychedelic experience a
conversation about these matters is
never closed about their insight here
that applies beyond altered states
whether you're watching on YouTube or
listening as a podcast remember to
subscribe and hit the bell to track
upcoming releases much of that's a click
one thing that is I hope all machines
I'm already doing it this has already
become self recursive I didn't even
express the thought and now we're
excluded from each other when I record
introductions to stuff that I post
uh-huh because there is like the lights
aren't on really so to speak there isn't
there imperative to actually maintain
dialogue with someone else you can sort
of stop it's like oh I misspoke or
something you're not you're not really
committed it's like yeah yeah you're not
you're not truly committed to the dance
and so I begin something and start
talking I'd be like you idiot
click that again there we go it's like
I'm back it's like good evening everyone
Reba god that's tiring find a way to get
out of that trap but it's like and then
I was thinking to myself don't break
what in you is able to actually commit
to this right now so that because that
is I suppose one technical definition of
wigging yourself out and you smoke too
much weed
it's like I'm stuck in it's like a
loop here that I can't quite get out of
and just move forward and there we go
loops
you know perhaps this is an experience
we've both shared on LSD for example or
in a psychedelic where you are trapped
in some sort of loop yes I wonder if I
could throw if I could throw something
at you here because this actually may be
something we can articulate with some it
might be helpful to some people watching
this and I want to be careful about any
sort of conversation to do with
psychedelics and flippin advocacy
because it's absolutely not the thing to
be flippant about no but these are
powerful tools that can be used for
great positive benefit god there's so
many there's so many disclaimers I even
want to add to that statement one thing
though that is experienced as a negative
experience for people is when when you
are trapped in some sort of thought loop
you can't escape
that seems the idea of that loop i seems
resonant to a lot of the stuff we've
been speaking about earlier so I wonder
if you could articulate what it is to be
stuck in a loop more broadly and then
perhaps how that shows up in
psychedelics and then what can be done
to alleviate or move through that
torture well yeah I've certainly been in
a few psychedelic loops that's for sure
mm-hmm and they have perhaps been the
most fruitful events when it comes to
navigating the mental loops that say
might come up in a sober mental
perspective it seems like those loops
exposed the fractal nature of the mind
trying to wrap itself around reality and
never quite being able to as reality is
propelled by novelty and so it is always
expanding and so the moment we have a
map you know
talked about before that that map never
quite fits reality because again we're
in a new more novel space again and that
does seem to be part of the teaching
with the psychedelic Bardot's to
actually for sure because Saito's can
you just just dimensions that you seem
to approach they're always like Timothy
Leary around us for a really beautiful
book the psychedelic experience which is
based on Bardot's kind of these levels
or you could say tests of awareness
through the psychedelics whereby you're
yeah you're tested almost by the
experience to see kind of where you're
at and they use the Tibetan Book of the
Dead to to kind of formulate these quite
poetic verses that you could use to help
someone through one of those experiences
you could read it yourself or someone
would read it out to someone else who's
having a heavy time in the trip but
aside from that it always seemed as if
any suffering I was experiencing with
within a psyche
psychedelic trip was some notion of
grasping some notion of mental
attachment and to the degree that I
didn't attach the psychedelics seemed to
accelerate that loop and also as they
accelerate it other reference points
seem to drop off so there's also a
conceptual dropping off of of other
things that you can grasp too so that
your mind is kind of forced and back
into a corner and one example of that I
would say is with LSD I had what what
happened was language fell away and
numerology was the only thing that was
left just numbers and eventually went
all the way down to just three to one
nothing one experience where for
probably an hour the only thing that my
ego was able to attach to was discerning
the differences between the Trinity then
duality and then there not being
anything anymore
and it would continuously go out and and
try to split that and the way this
manifests there was a friend my friend
who was tripping with me and my cat
mm-hmm
which entered the room and I couldn't
figure out if there was three
individuals mm-hmm or if no the cat
wasn't really involved in the experience
and it was just me and my friend to ghen
right so just to again yeah but then I
felt like I was seeing from Tegan's
perspective myself right and that so
there was actually only one being yes
and that seemed to loop around for
eternity whether or not it was the cat
involved yet a sermon or just all
there's three of us and there's two of
us and there's one and there's nothing
and it just kept looping and looping it
was yeah there was pretty it was
difficult very difficult wasn't
necessary suffering but I've to shift
away from my own personal experience
I've heard that mirrored in many others
too right well there's been a
self-referential loop right that seems
to drop down to something very
simplistic that they can't escape right
so all other reference points of reality
seem to have
fallen apart and now it's just been this
dance between two things that they can't
get out of yes and so the only way out
of it the only way out of it is is
through again the surrender of mind
sandrov mental grasping so that you just
allow reality again to be as it is and I
could give you countless other examples
of that whereby the solution has been
surrender and I suppose that often
conjures up a vibe of apathy within
others to just surrender and let it go
but it it seems to be the real act of
courage to just say do you know what I
don't know actually
and when you allow that not knowing to
come paradoxically it's like you're
rewarded with more than you could have
ever imagined
and often yeah that is it that does seem
to be some kind of dissolving away of
conditioning that you've had from the
past or or some limiting belief all
right around your identity which
actually dissolves with that experience
mm-hmm so I can accepting of the loop in
some sense isn't heart accepting a
decent synonym there for surrender
yeah I would say so is an accepting of
reality mm-hmm it's it's almost like you
give up trying to add anything
do you give up the need for it to be
another way mm-hmm is that perhaps
mm-hmm a good way to absolutely yeah
right yeah yeah yeah you know a lot of
the times we're unhappy because because
we want things to be different mm-hmm
there's a real liberation to wanting
what's actually happening right now
mm-hmm
so accepting what's happening and that's
what you mean by that though accepting
it is in some sense a valuing of it for
itself just as it is and the wanting
would be well we want to be in touch
with what is the process of moving all
of that so that is that uh-huh yeah for
sure because what's happening here in
the psychedelic experience and not even
necessary just psyche - I mean I think
this really happens a lot in in yoga a
lot actually you're building fire in the
body you're giving space through these
asanas freeze postural movements you
you're allowing you're allowing certain
thoughts and habits and conditioned
thinking to arise you're witnessing it
with presence and it's strange actually
some postures seem to to be more
provocative in that sense than others
and you're giving space to that and
you're watching them come up and it's
very similar to a psychedelic experience
and then that kind of shavasana where
they lie in the corpse pose at the end
is actually like an integration process
it's after all these movements you then
steal the body and just allow what's
happened to just settle a little like a
muddied lake all muddied river has kind
of bent world up and at the end you just
kind of let it sit and let things be as
they are but certainly something that's
worth pointing out is that the reason
why you're accepting and letting
is actually because the things that
you're holding on to don't actually have
their illusions they don't a lot the
time they're the things that aren't
actually there their mind made you know
whether that's like a again some some
conditioning around the way that your
navigator ality that is based on an
experience you have when you were
younger that that doesn't have any any
value actually to your present
experience right it happened but it
doesn't have any value now and you're
holding on to it is is giving it fuel
and that and then by letting go of it
we're kind of throwing it into the fire
in some ways we're not we're not
negating it we're allowing it to be
mm-hmm beautiful yes I agree with you I
think that the the accepting of our
delusion is an important seems to me
right now an interesting turn of phrase
I find Wilbur's thought immense in
particular the the synthesis of so much
process to the terms to the phrase
transcend and include mm-hmm the sense
in which you awaken enable activate grow
into a more in touch perspective but
that in so doing you aren't as you put
it negating mm-hmm in entirety the the
the value released the lineage of the
value of a particular impulse or
perspective
one of the experiences I've taken from
navigating psychedelics in particular a
navigation towards greater intensity or
depth associated perhaps with what
people refer to as breaking through
which i think is relative anyway because
once your cup has been once your cup is
full or overflowed like it could be a
pond or a lake or an ocean
you're just a full cup at that point you
know it's like there can be that voice
well it's let's there is that voice of
course let's say of concern off of pain
I'm losing something let's go back let's
stop this this voice associated with the
fear of death often mm-hmm it's like the
attitude I've found and I think this
syncs up with what you're saying the
attitude I found to be helpful it is not
an attitude of like God that there's
that voice again you just stop that
thing you know don't be don't don't take
a back to it don't don't don't bully it
accept it right it's a you know what you
can come along too I know you're just
looking out for me you know obviously
you should care this button crazy what's
going on right now
I think obviously you can we should like
there's a there's a is a beauty to
wanting to preserve as well you know it
but anything out of balance is an issue
and so it's it's an accepting and but
nevertheless nevertheless an opening and
a moving forward mmm so and yes it's
like sure then we discovered that the
thoughts that we've I've been
identifying with or that previous
conception that we've come to identify
as ourselves that narrative self or
fixed ego self for at least some period
of time is in some sense an illusion
but more a stage of development I would
say more just not the final incarnation
and sure we might say it it in its
fixation never truly grasp the world but
it was representative it was Co a
current with lived being at least for
that agent that consciousness you know
which was navigating as it was and so
there is that to be respected because
God the the the delusion the capacity
for delusion and self-deception it's not
that's not going anywhere
you know that's coming with us all the
way so the danger is always to in in
resenting in resenting a part of your
eternal nature this is something to
worry about something to take seriously
so it's like some sort of radical
self-acceptance required even if that
part of you is oh ultimately at one
level a precursor or the younger version
you know of what it is you you one day
will grow into here we should probably
have a look and research that was a nice
little segment now I know we put
something together there that's going to
terrify our mothers and perhaps three
psychedelically minded young people
[Music]
the Trinity of the cat and the other
human was something that I'll never
forget whether you're watching on
YouTube or listening as a podcast
remember to subscribe and hit the bell
to track upcoming releases much of